<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xml:id="chapter-overview"
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
    xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="
        http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd
        http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd">
  <title>Overview</title>
  
  <section>
    <title>Why Asta4D</title>
    <para>In the past decade, plenty of Java based web application frameworks are generated. Especially the MVC 
    architecture and JSP tag libs (or other traditional template technologies) that has greatly released our productivity. 
    But unfortunately, we are still suffering from the following situations:
    </para>
    
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The designers or front-end engineers are keeping complaining the mixed-in dynamic code, as they disturb 
        their efforts of redesigning the page style or structure. And in the mean time, the back-end developers are also 
        complaining that the front-end guys break the working page frequently,  because redesign or the new design is hard 
        to merge due to the huge cost of source refactorying. </para>
        <sbr/>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The developers are complaining about the poor functionalities of template language which they are using 
        and tired from the various magic skills for complex rendering logic.</para>
        <sbr/>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The developers are discontented with the counterproductivity of traditional MVC architecture and desire a more efficient 
        approach.</para>
        <sbr/>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>How Asta4D helps us</title>
    <para>Asta4D is our solution to combat those issues. Thanks to lift, from where we learn a lot. We designed Asta4D complying
    with the following points:
    </para>
    
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Separate template and rendering logic</para>
        <para>Asta4D affords front-end engineers a friendly environment by separating rendering logic from template files which
        are pure html files. At the mean time, back-end engineers can use the powerful Java language to implement the rendering
        logic without being suffering from the "poor and sometimes magic" template languages.
        </para>
        <sbr/>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Testable rendering logic</para>
        <para>All of the rendering logic in Asta4D is testable and developers can simply test them by writing simple junit cases, 
        which could replace over than half of selenium tests</para>
        <sbr/>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
        <para>High security of being immune from cross-site(XSS/CSRF)</para>
        <para>Asta4D is, by nature, immune from cross-site(XSS/CSRF) problems. You do not need to take care of cross-site any more. 
        All the rendered value would be escaped by default and your clients have no chance to put malicious contents to your server.
        </para>
        <sbr/>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
        <para>View first</para>
        <para>Asta4D also affords higher productivity than traditional MVC architecture by View First mechanism. And it is also easier 
        to change than traditional MVC architecture.
        </para>
        <sbr/>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
        <para>Isolate side effect with request handler</para>
        <para>Asta4D imports the conception of "side-effect" from functional programming languages and separating the "side-effect"
        by request handlers, which afford more flexibility on page rendering because the view layer is side-effect free now. Therefore
        Asta4D allows parallel page rendering in multiple threads as a built-in feature.
        </para>
        <sbr/>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
        <para>Advanced MVC</para>
        <para>Asta4D affords developers a evolved MVC architecture which is more clarified for the duty of each application layer than
        the traditional MVC architecture. 
        </para>
        <sbr/>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>What does the name of "Asta4D" mean</title>
    <para>The name of Asta4D is from our company's name: astamuse. We explain the "4D" as following ways:</para> 
    
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>For Designer</para>
        <para>Asta4D consider the design friendliness as the most important factor of itself. We hope web designers can fulfil their
        maximum potential of creativity without squandering their time on the back-end technologies which they could never be adept at.
        </para>
        <sbr/>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>For developer</para>
        <para>We hope Asta4D can help developers to achieve their work more easily. Developers would never be afflicted with complex
        rendering logic because they can use powerful Java language to do whatever they want since the rendering has been split from
        template files. View first also releases developers from the cumbersome MVC architecture, now they have more time to have a cup
        of coffee.</para>
        <sbr/>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
        <para>4 Dimension</para>
        <para>We believe that Asta4D can act as a wormhole that connects the front-end and the back-end. We can move quicker by Asta4D just
        like we are going through the 4 dimensional space.
        </para>
        <sbr/>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>