<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xml:id="chapter-side-effect"
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
    xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="
        http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd
        http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd">
  <title>Side effect and request handler</title>
 
  <section>
    <title>The role with responsibility to http request: Request Handler</title>
    <para>
    Even Asta4D complies with the principle of view first, there is still a role similar with the controller in MVC
    architecture, such role is called request handler. We believe that there should be a role who takes responsiblity
    of a certain http request and such role can be considered as an alternative to controller of MVC in some situations
    too.
    </para>
    
    <para>
    According to the view first rule, a request handler can be ignored in most cases. You can also assume that there is
    is a default request handler which navigates all the http requests to the corresponding template files(The real 
    story is more complex but you can try to understand the theory conceptually by this way).
    </para>
    
    <para>
    Now the question is when we need a request handler? Before we can answer this question, we have to discuss the conception
    of "side effect".
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Side effect of system operations</title>

    <para>
    A system always afford users various operations such as query, update, etc. All of these operations will affect the status
    of system in various ways. In Asta4D, we say that there are two types of action in a system, one is with “side effect”, 
    another one is without “side effect”. “actions with side effect” are ones that will change the system status once they are
    performed. For instance, for the same URL, a login request (if succeeded) will cause a client’s privilege to be changed and 
    the client could probably get a different page view from what the client get before login, because of which we say a login 
    request is an action with side effect. Another obvious example is a database update operation. Once an update is committed, 
    all the related clients will get a different output from the result before the update, which is also classified as “an action 
    with side effect”. 
    </para>
    
    <para>
    How about a query? We consider a query as an operation without side effect, it means that a client will always get the same
    result regardless of how many times the query is executed. Some people may ask how about counting on query times? For counting
    on query times, we can still split the counting and query to two individual operations, one is with side effect and another one
    is without side effect.
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Isolate side effect and multi thread rendering</title>

    <para>
    We believe the actions with side effect should be managed seriously and we do that by putting all the actions with side effect
    to request handlers so that the view layer is purified and this makes the source more clear and maintainable. This is also means 
    with Asta4D we can easily perform multi thread rendering on a single page because they are now all side-effect free, which is a
    high light function of Asta4D.
    </para>

    <para>
    In traditional MVC architecture, the responsibility of controller is tangled, a controller does not only handle the duty of altering
    system status(date update), but also takes the responsibility of preparing data for view layer. We often have to expand the database
    session(transaction) to the view layer for handling lazy load issue, which makes transaction management more complicated. Additionally,
    especially for the pages that can be split to relatively individual blocks, hypothetically we can accelerate the page loading
    by retrieving data in multi threads for each block, but in reality it is impossible due to the source complexity and development costs.
    The developers still have to access each data source sequentially to retrieve data for each block even the page is splitable as individual
    blocks.
    </para>

    <para>
    For Asta4D, the logic layers of system is clarified by isolating side effects at architecture level. The database session(transaction)
    does no longer need keep opening cross layers, it is clear that the duty of request handler is altering system status but not preparing
    data for view layer. At the mean time, at the view layer, acquiring data and rendering data are performed at the same time, at the same
    place: We access data source and retrieve data in snippet method, and pass the data to Renderer to perform rendering immediately in the
    same snippet method. Further, the complexity can be reduced drastically because all the accesses to certain data are isolated in certain
    snippet methods and there is no cross layer invoking and coupling any more.
    </para>
    
    <para>
    On the other hand, we can simply perform multi thread rendering by calling each snippet method in different threads, which is transparent to
    developer. Because all the side effects has been isolated in request handler layer, we do not need to considerate sync or mutex even we
    are performing multi thread rendering since the view layer is side effect free now.
    </para>
    
    <para>
    Let us see how easy we can achieve parallel rendering 
    </para>
    
    <example>
      <programlisting language="xml">
<![CDATA[
<div afd:render="ParallelTest$TestRender:snippetInDiv" afd:parallel>  
    <div id="test">xx</div>  
</div>  
  
<afd:snippet render="ParallelTest$TestRender:snippetReplaceDiv" parallel>  
    <div id="test">xx</div>  
</afd:snippet>
]]>
      </programlisting>
      <para>
      All the snippets declared with parallel(afd:parallel) attribution will not block the http request main thread, the http request main thread
      will wait for the parallel rendering after all the non-parallel rendering finished, then merge the result and output to the client.
      </para>
    </example>
  </section>

<!--  
  <section>
    <title>Compatibility to MVC</title>
    <para>
    Someone may ask: "Is it true that we do not need MVC?", "Is it true that we do not need a controller?". The answer is "No". We
    admit that MVC architecture is more convenient than view first for some certain cases, for instance, when we are handling form
    submission, the MVC structure is required naturally. By Asta4D, you can simply handle this case by implement the request handler
    as a controller.
    </para>
    
    <para>
    Further, perhaps you cannot agree with the idea of view first. You believe a controller is necessary in any case but you are also
    interested in the split template mechanism of Asta4D, the same answer for you: implement your request handler as a controller. 
    </para>
    
    <para>
      <remark>You can also integrate Asta4D's template only as a view layer implementation for Spring MVC. More details can be found in reference.</remark>
    </para>
  </section>
-->

</chapter>